Classical optimization is a crucial step in classical quantum algorithms
古典的な最適化は、古典量子アルゴリズムにおける重要なステップです。
like the variational quantum eigensolver or quantum machine learning.
変分量子固有値ソルバーや量子機械学習などがその例です。
However, often it turns out to be difficult to minimize
しかし、最小化が難しいケースも多くあります。
complicated functions in high dimensional parameters spaces.
高次元パラメータ空間における複雑な関数がその典型です。
My name is Victoria Lipinska and in this video we'll explore
私はVictoria Lipinskaです。このビデオでは、
classical optimization routines for classical quantum algorithms.
古典量子アルゴリズムにおける古典的最適化の手法を探っていきます。
Optimization problems are not easy.
最適化問題は簡単ではありません。
When the number of parameters grows, so does the number of possible
パラメータの数が増えると、取り得る値の組み合わせも
combinations of values, and it grows exponentially.
指数関数的に増加していきます。
In chess, for example, there are 64 spaces
チェスを例に考えてみましょう。盤面には64マスがあり、
and each player has 16 pieces after each player moves a single piece,
各プレイヤーは16個の駒を持っています。それぞれが1手指した後、
there are 400 different positions. After two moves 72,084 positions,
盤面のパターンは400通り。2手後は72,084通り、
around 9 million after three and around
3手後は約900万通り、そして
280 billion after four moves.
4手後には約2,800億通りにも達します。
If we reach only 40 moves, the number of possible positions
40手まで進んだ場合、可能な局面の数は
is estimated to be around ten to the power of 120.
10の120乗ほどになると推定されています。
Playing a perfect game would require exploring all possible
完璧なゲームを指すには、すべての可能な局面を
positions and this enormous growth means that going through
探索する必要があります。この膨大な数を考えると、
all positions individually is unfeasible.
すべての局面を個別に調べるのは現実的ではありません。
This can be solved by breaking the problem into two smaller sub-problems.
この問題は、2つの小さなサブ問題に分解することで解決できます。
First, we need to determine which setups of the chessboard
まず、今後のゲームの展開に現れそうな
are likely to appear in future steps of our game.
盤面の状態を特定する必要があります。
We'll call this our subspace of interest.
これを「注目する部分空間」と呼びましょう。
And second, given that subspace, we must determine what move is best.
次に、その部分空間を前提として、最善手を決定します。
We'll call this our best move.
これを「最善手」と呼びます。
In this analogy, the initial search through the subspace of interest
このたとえで言えば、注目する部分空間を最初に探索する作業が
is the analog of our classical optimization algorithm.
古典的最適化アルゴリズムに相当します。
Once that subspace of interest is known,
その部分空間が特定されると、
a quantum algorithm is usually responsible for finding the best move,
通常は量子アルゴリズムが最善手を見つける役割を担います。
given that subspace.
その部分空間の中から最善を選ぶわけです。
Let's start with considering just one parameter,
まず、パラメータが1つだけの場合を考えてみましょう。
theta, parameterizing a cost function which we wish to optimize.
パラメータthetaでコスト関数をパラメータ化し、それを最適化します。
If we plot the function, say it looks something like this,
関数をプロットすると、例えばこのような形になるとします。
on the X-axis we have values of the parameter theta
X軸にはパラメータthetaの値が並び、
and on the y axis there's the cost function.
Y軸にはコスト関数の値が表示されます。
Keep in mind the cost function could be an actual financial cost
コスト関数は、実際の財務的なコストである場合もありますし、
we wish to minimize or as is often the case in the variational quantum
変分量子固有値ソルバーでよく見られるように、
eigensolver, it could be an energy that is minimized by nature.
自然界が最小化するエネルギーである場合もあります。
Our objective is to find the theta
目的は、コストが最も低くなる
that corresponds to the lowest cost.
thetaの値を見つけることです。
We start with an initial value of theta and in every optimization step
thetaの初期値から始めて、最適化のステップごとに
we find a new theta that decreases the cost further.
コストをさらに下げる新しいthetaを探していきます。
It seems like we know pretty easily which way to proceed on the graph if we're able to see it.
グラフが見えていれば、どちらの方向に進めばよいかは直感的にわかります。
But the difficulty in optimization is that we actually don't.
しかし最適化の難しさは、実際にはそれが見えないことにあります。
We only find out the cost so a tiny piece of the whole puzzle,
選んだthetaで関数を評価して初めて、
once we evaluate the function on the selected theta.
パズルのほんの一片、つまりコストの値がわかるだけです。
This is the general way optimization works.
これが最適化の基本的な仕組みです。
The optimizer samples parameters theta and calculates the cost.
オプティマイザーはパラメータthetaをサンプリングし、コストを計算します。
As you can imagine, randomly choosing the parameter theta to reconstruct
想像できるように、thetaをランダムに選んで関数全体の形を
the whole topology of the function is not very efficient.
再構築しようとするのは、あまり効率的ではありません。
Instead, what smart optimizers do is finding
そこで、賢いオプティマイザーは各ステップで
the gradient of the function in each step.
関数の勾配を求めます。
This way the optimizer knows which direction on the plot
これにより、最小コストを見つけるために
to follow in order to find the smallest cost.
グラフ上のどの方向に進むべきかがわかります。
Once the gradient is zero, the algorithm terminates,
勾配がゼロになると、アルゴリズムは終了し、
and the minimum is found.
最小値が見つかったことになります。
This minimum might not be the global minimum.
ただし、この最小値はグローバル最小値とは限りません。
It may be a local minimum,
ローカル最小値である可能性もあります。
meaning it's the smallest value of the cost function in the neighborhood
つまり、近傍ではコスト関数が最小値を取りますが、
but not across the whole range of theta.
thetaの全範囲で見ると最小ではない場合です。
In the case of one parameter, that's certainly possible.
パラメータが1つの場合でも、それは十分あり得ます。
However, the more parameters we have,
パラメータの数が増えるにつれて、
the more complicated the function becomes.
関数はさらに複雑になっていきます。
Already, in the case of two parameters, we have a surface,
パラメータが2つになるだけで曲面になりますし、
and in the case of four, we can't even draw it anymore.
4つになるともはや描くことすらできません。
Just like in the chess example, reproducing all possibilities
チェスの例と同様に、すべての可能性を網羅しようとすると
quickly becomes intractable.
すぐに手に負えなくなります。
We see that it's difficult to minimize
このように、高次元パラメータ空間における
complicated functions in high dimensional parameter spaces.
複雑な関数の最小化は困難です。
However, to get reasonable results, we want classical optimization
それでも実用的な結果を得るためには、古典的最適化の
routines to be both fast and accurate.
手法が高速かつ正確であることが求められます。
They also need to be robust to noise,
また、ノイズに対して頑健である必要もあります。
which will have significant effect in near-term quantum computers.
ノイズは近未来の量子コンピュータにおいて大きな影響を与えます。
Classical optimization algorithms can be broadly divided
古典的最適化アルゴリズムは大きく2種類に分けられます。
into two classes - direct search and gradient based methods.
直接探索法と勾配ベースの手法の2種類です。
Gradient based methods require information about the gradient
勾配ベースの手法では、最適化の過程で
of the function during the optimization process.
関数の勾配に関する情報が必要です。
This can either be computed analytically
この勾配は解析的に計算することも、
or approximated in a finite difference calculation.
有限差分計算で近似することもできます。
Direct search methods do not use gradient information
直接探索法は勾配情報を使わず、
and use other strategies to minimize the cost function.
別の戦略でコスト関数を最小化します。
Some of the most commonly used optimization algorithms
量子コンピューティングの分野でよく使われる
in the quantum computing landscape are the following optimizers.
最適化アルゴリズムには、次のものがあります。
COBYLA stands for constrained optimization by linear approximation
COBYLAは「線形近似による制約付き最適化」の略で、
and it is a gradient-free optimization algorithm.
勾配を使わない最適化アルゴリズムです。
SLSQP is sequential least squares programming,
SLSQPは「逐次最小二乗法プログラミング」の略で、
a gradient based optimization algorithm.
勾配ベースの最適化アルゴリズムです。
It uses a stochastic perturbation vector
SPSAは確率的な摂動ベクトルを使って、
to simultaneously compute an approximate gradient of the cost function.
コスト関数の近似勾配を同時に計算します。
In a noiseless environment, optimizers like COBYLA
ノイズのない環境では、COBYLAのような
and SLSQP were found to converge faster than SPSA.
オプティマイザーやSLSQPはSPSAより速く収束することがわかっています。
Classical optimizers have their own parameters
古典的なオプティマイザーにはそれぞれ固有のパラメータがあり、
that you can specify for particular cases, for example, step size.
特定のケースに合わせてステップサイズなどを指定できます。
Those can typically be found in documentation related
これらのパラメータは通常、各オプティマイザーに
to the specific optimizer.
関連するドキュメントで確認できます。
I encourage you to check the references list below for a comparison
最新の古典的オプティマイザーの比較については、
of the most up to date classical optimizers.
下記の参考文献リストをぜひご覧ください。
Let's explore one more phenomenon connected
もう一つ、パラメータ化された量子 circuit の
to classical optimization of parameterized quantum circuits.
古典的最適化に関連する現象を見ていきましょう。
As we saw before, a vanishing gradient of the cost function can indicate
先ほど見たように、コスト関数の勾配が消えることは、
that the optimizer ended up on a plateau with no interesting features, a so-called
オプティマイザーが特徴のない平坦な領域、いわゆる
"barren plateau."
「barren plateau（不毛高原）」に陥ったことを示している可能性があります。
A barren plateau can be a result of many factors.
barren plateauはさまざまな要因によって生じます。
The gradient of the cost function corresponding to a quantum circuit
ランダムに初期化されたパラメータを持つ量子 circuit に対応する
with randomly initialized parameters
コスト関数の勾配は、
decays exponentially to zero with the number of qubits.
qubitの数に応じて指数関数的にゼロへ減衰します。
This is because the quantum space explored by the optimizer
これは、オプティマイザーが探索する量子空間が
becomes exponentially large when the number of qubits increases.
qubitの数の増加とともに指数関数的に大きくなるためです。
The ways to tackle this problem include reducing the number of parameters
この問題に対処する方法の一つは、パラメータの数を減らし、
and therefore the dimension of the underlying space.
基礎となる空間の次元を小さくすることです。
Another way to think of the origin of the barren plateau issue
barren plateauの問題の起源について別の見方をすると、
could be the problem agnostic nature of the parameterized circuit
パラメータ化された circuit が問題に依存しない設計になっており、
faced with exponentially large parameter space.
指数関数的に大きなパラメータ空間に直面していることが考えられます。
Designing a circuit in the way tailored to the considered
対象とする問題に合わせた形で circuit を
problem could be a good solution.
設計することが、有効な解決策になりえます。
Besides the exponential parameter space that induces barren plateaus,
barren plateauを引き起こす指数的なパラメータ空間に加え、
other physical phenomena can also generate them:
他の物理的な現象もbarren plateauを生じさせることがあります。
the noise and decoherence present in the quantum computing experiments,
量子コンピューティングの実験に伴うノイズとデコヒーレンス、
the overall expressibility of the parameterized circuit,
パラメータ化されたcircuitの表現能力（expressibility）、
or nonlocality and degree of entanglement of the cost function modeled.
またはモデル化されたコスト関数の非局所性とエンタングルメントの程度などです。
It remains an active area of research to address these challenges.
これらの課題への対応は、現在も活発に研究が続いています。
Having now reviewed the principal components of VQE,
VQEの主要なコンポーネントを一通り確認しましたので、
we'll summarize the algorithm in the next video.
次のビデオでアルゴリズム全体をまとめます。